Hi all, good evening, am I audible and visible guys, yes great, thank you Abhinav, give me
a second, I'll share my screen, yeah I will do that, okay we'll do that, please let me
know if you can see my screen, screen share is visible right, yeah great thank you, so
I wanted to ask one thing like you know there's a drop in number of people who have solved
assignments for the last class css one, is it because of attendance or you had any challenge,
I just want to understand if you had any challenge or those straightforward or anything you have
faced it, anyone, okay let's see we have 16 people in the class, how many of you
have solved it, if you have solved it give me thumbs up, if you haven't tried it give me thumbs down
okay
great, so among them three what could be the possible reason guys like you were not able to
find time or like any challenges or if I can help you out, okay great Abhinav, time,
sure it would take I think believe me this full stack related assignments right
shouldn't be taking more than half an hour for you to solve them like two three questions so
maybe you can try it down okay because I don't want your backlog to you know fill up
right so people who gave me thumbs down right please try to you know manage it
and give your you know like time some time to it at least half an hour or one hour whatever it is
like depending on your speed okay so yeah no worries Abhishek please
just cover it up only you have two classes right so moving forward you won't have that backlog
okay thank you Abhishek, so guys anyone can drop message in whatsapp again
would be really helpful like we are getting started
frequently traveling because of work from different state to state
state to state
Dhanraj where do you work
uh can you add that as a question like I'll try to take it commonly like this
you have your own business okay
okay let's let's do one thing guys what we'll do is like
firstly we'll revise what we have discussed in session one then we'll get started okay
I'll drop a message in group give me a second yeah Tejal has dropped a message
thank you Tejal thank you Raman
okay great so let's
okay guys you can discuss with Abhishek discuss with Dhanraj later on but he maybe he's trying
to build his career in IT let's focus on that last part okay so
we'll get started guys it's seven of nine oh five already okay so today's agenda is
morally specifically based on box model display and position these three particular fields
particular fields but before going on to that I want you to you know shoot the something that
you remember what we have learned in last last class like what you have learned or what we have
discussed so what are the sections css we have introduced right we talked about what is css then
we have discussed what is inline css
selectors
then we have discussed colors right if you remember colors and font and background property
these are the things that we introduced already in last class now just trying to revise guys
trying to revise if you come to selectors what all selectors you have
like what all selectors you have can I say id then you have something called as class
after that you have element selector then you have attribute selector
these are the simple selectors that you can see other than this thing you have combinatorics
when you go for combinatorics combinations you have descendant selector
descendant selector
and then you have children's selector right we have discussed all of this so I hope all
these things are basic things are clear right how do you access a particular field using id class
attribute descendant and children right okay great now if you have also seen about colors like
how many types of how many ways you can choose colors what all things are there guys
three right what would be the first way like you want to select directly you can directly
write it down blue green red what we have limitation how many colors this way we can
add it 140 right great right but what was the second way of doing it rgba function
where r goes for red then green then blue then alpha goes for opacity like how much
transparency you need it in color right then you also had hex code hex code again starts with hash
then rr bb gg right then you had hsl we stand for hue saturation
and what was l rise lightness right
right this was from 0 to 360 which is used to manage the red and this was for
like saturation 0 to 100 you can give it this also goes for 0 to 100
which is used to you know darker or lighter and this used to generate
different shades of a particular color right
what is 255
255 was this one right 0 to 255 was the range for this one right yeah great no worries
after this we also discussed background right and background what all things we have discussed
right like one thing we had is image like how we can add an image or a background image right
then how can you center it or you know position it right so we had discussed about background
properties if i put it in there are many properties in background but we have discussed about
background in general repeat no repeat like if you want to repeat or gently if you want to
repeat that vertically right so these are things that we have discussed also we have seen fonts
like how we can import the fonts of different like if you want extra things which are other
than the browser which will provide support if you can download from google fonts link your
api google api and then attach your fonts and you can use them in the font family property
right so i hope this is something that we have discussed and there are no doubts on this right
if there are no doubts we can get started with today's class guys
yeah great great guys let's let's get started with today now first thing that i want to discuss
is that few properties i want to talk about on font and text right so these are the two things
which are that will be for the total positive if we import and use that in app yeah yeah right
some bit so it will be you can use it like wherever you want to define it for each element or every
element font you can use it okay depends on it like if you want to use it for the whole project
or like it's your specifications what your ux designer or your if you are designing your own
app you can define it okay i've just showed you the way you can do it it's up to you how
you want to do it okay now so guys uh so let's start with font and text these are the two short
properties that i want to discuss first because if you go and see right uh the most of the websites
any website you pick it up in today's world every site is filled with most of the content in it
right where you consume the data like reading website you go for geek for geeks you go for
medium.com or you go for the reference material that i was giving you it has more of a text
content isn't it other than streaming apps that you see more of the apps or everything that you
have is more of a content text right related to or you can say typography right so we'll see
what are the properties that are available on the text and what all things you can deal with
okay so i'll create one html file and we'll see like what all things you can apply firstly
this is again referring to the same thing let's say you go open a microsoft word or anything
and you start let's say typing it down a content or a paragraph that you write in microsoft excel
and what all things you deal with okay so the same things that what what you can do it in
microsoft excel will be able to we should be able to do all of them so let's see okay i hope my
vs code is visible guys
okay thank you so let's say i'm using m8 again i would say this is font and
text part okay now let's say i have one h1 tag so
uh okay munishwar i'll push it this is heading one uh and i'm using another paragraph p tag again
i'm using lorem 20 so let's say i've generated this code now i'll try to open it in show preview
on the right side let's say i minimize this now let's say we open style block here to write down
let's say we open style block here to write down all the styles we have
now so last time in last class we have discussed like related to font
like font already font family right let's say we use it again okay one is a font family which used
to change the type of fonts that we are using like if you see the current current one we can
change it by using any of the font family that you have let's say i've used this for heading
you see the heading type of the style that heading is generally applicable is changing let's say we
apply that other thing so this thing i've already shown you that if you want it even you can uh
change the like you know you can if you the particular properties if whichever are available
if not enough you can also import it right so let's say i'm using here
uh georgia times new sheriff then let's say i also use for paragraph where
font family let's say this one okay so font family was something we have already discussed in last
class now i want to talk something let's say this heading how do you like other than the font like
the height of this word what is the difference between this one and this one guys what do you
see a difference between two two of these lines other than the height
other than the height like what do you see the difference boldness right so if you if can we
make this particular paragraph content also increase the boldness and spacing agree right
so we'll try to do something like such that we can make this you know paragraph track convert
into h1 somehow so if you want to increase or play around with the boldness of a particular
paragraph or a content right you can always use a one property called font weight which keeps your
value from 0 100 to 900 and or else if you can use it by words you can use it by words like lighter
bolder let's say if we use lighter it is still the same but what if we use bold see that converted
into bold but if i convert into bolder it will be same way as you see it for the h1
okay or else you can give 800 or 900 this all things again define on the same range of lighter
bold and bolder okay this font weight here guys what font weight does for us
right now the other thing imagine like if you want to increase the size of this paragraph size
equal to like h1 let's say we want this paragraph to be equivalent to h1 somehow
and we do it or use can we do it some achieve that or do we have any property if anyone knows
right let's say there is one property already i've got suggestions right font size so even
you have font size using that you can always deal with it it takes all the types of yeah so
i was talking about like can we convert this paragraph size like the size of the words you
can see to the size of this one or you can increase the size okay let's say font size again
font says what are the least of values it takes okay so different types of units i haven't introduced
it like pixels em or rem right relative units so we'll discuss them in the future classes but for
now consider there are the pixels now pixels are like each screen can have a depending on a screen
width and height it have a list of size of pixels now you have to define in the terms of like how
many pixels that you want to cover on a screen okay similarly let's say you also have this
you know words given due like like large larger medium small and smaller which again define the
different size of sizes so i'm using just by default like larger which will be converting into
nearly same side of font okay others if you want to convert into it directly like you can give a
30 pixel okay which is like let's say 28 pixel is something i guess equivalent to
h1 heading okay now we have converted two of the things now but there is something
let's say what if you want to move anything let's say the content right if i let's say i expand it
okay let's say i make this as a low ram 10
okay now if you see what's happening is that it's taking full space and full width but what i
wanted to show you guys is that let's say i'm having a div here
okay i'm adding some css guys i'm converting this div into container
okay i'm having a border of two pixels solid i'll talk about this one
black and let's say i also give height of
400 pixel and let's say width of 100 percent
okay now let's say this now there is something let's say if you see this word side this whatever
paragraph and h1 tags are there all of them are left aligned right all of them are left aligned
do you guys agree with this they are left aligned right they are starting from the left most like
if you take a note you start writing from the left left most writing right but if you go for
some languages like urdu they write it from right side right they start it from right side and they
they come back they that's how they write it what if we have such kind of languages or
what we have such kind of scripts if you want to move it from the start the content left or right
for that also we have one of the field called anyone does know it anyone do do you know it
text align right where you want to align the text let's say if i put it end if you see like as you
see maybe it didn't convert like this is the heading from the reverse but if you see that
content has been pushed to the end okay now imagine if i have this in the span tag
span tag again this is heading one
okay and let's say that i say i say i have a span
and text align left let's say center
do you see guys span for this particular text align is not being applied for the center
do you see this text align is not working for the span tag so i'll keep that open-ended question
for some time what i'll do i'll do i'll go into us like i'll go and apply text align center
for the paragraph meanwhile okay it converted into center so i've kept open this span uh so
this one difference that you can find it like between these three types of elements can anyone
figure it out what is the difference in this so shant has said in line span is not a block
element span is right so what what exactly meant is guys like let's say when you go for h1
let's say when you go for h1 and paragraph these are block level elements so only there
are few css properties that applies for the block level elements and the few properties
which doesn't apply for inline because inline takes only the amount of space it needs it starts
from the place where you have defined it and it ends at the place where it is like the content if
it space is whatever content it has once it occupies that space it doesn't do anything like
you cannot change its location because the if you see uh let's open this uh particular thing
uh in the live server open in live server uh give me a second guys
yeah we can use it shortly now
if you see this inline element right the span tag is ending here itself but when i go for h1
if you see it's occupying whole row when there is a space of row in the whole row it can move left
right center right but when it when it is like when it's occupying only the amount of space it needs
it's occupying only the amount of space it needs then you cannot move it because the space is
already fulfilled do you guys understand why first this property is not applying
anyone having any doubt on this why uh you know this text alignment is not working on span tag
okay thank you guys okay so what i mean to say is that uh arun tejal okay okay so firstly
if you come and see here i have used three types of elements one is h1 one is span and one is
paragraph h1 and paragraph are block level elements whenever you go for block level elements
it takes whole space like whole row space like if you see this is a block level element it is
taking whole row space if you go for this paragraph it is taking whole row doesn't matter how much
content it is having or it doesn't have it okay but when it comes to span it is taking only the
amount of space it needs it it is not consuming whole space whole row space is this point clear
tejal arun hariprasad ankit right so now what happening is let's say i have more amount of
space if let's say if you go into the uh train and the whole coach is empty you can set it in
any table but if it is only one set you will be able to go and sit in only that set right
but here if you see the for this uh block level elements there is a space it can move left right
bottom anywhere i mean it has a start end and uh and like start end and center only three places
right so what we have done is like we told that whenever you go for block level elements
textile and property will be used to assign elements to the left right or the center it
will apply for only block level elements because it they consume whole space of a row
i hope this point is clear now and it won't apply for the span level elements because these are
inline elements okay great guys now coming to the next property once textile and we completed
excellent now there's something called let's say you you remember there are like if you go for
microsoft word or google docs you have like underlines you know strike off through the
content that you have right so we'll try to apply if we can do that same property since
there's a heading available for us this is a heading okay
let's say text decoration some width will discuss them one by one okay
not going completely in depth because if i cover each and every property classes might not be
enough you have to explore few i'll explore explain few of things in that okay it's like
both the ways okay we'll see but i'll explain that part if you go for text decoration if you see
there is something like if you see uh overline if you see overland what overland does it like
adds over the heading so there are basic three properties that you use generally for the text
decoration one is overline then there is something called underline which adds you know underline
over the heading then there is something called line through which cuts the line these are the
three things that you keep on using in the words right or you are preparing any documentation or
you're writing things these are the basic three things type of decorations that you use with the
text isn't it so i'll use this underline here
as of now i hope this point is clear what does text decoration gives us
right then there is some someone told me right there's a you know word spacing there's a word
spacing difference between this is heading and this lot of paragraph content if you want to give
a spacing or increase of spacing right between words there's a property again you have something
like word spacing you can go and add word spacing let's say you go for and say two pixel now if you
see once i gave two pixel this both looks like a line bit of a line right so word spacing generally
gives a space between the words and there is something another property called line spacing
which gives
sorry letter spacing which gives space between the letters let's say i give to 0.2 pixel
okay so there are two things word spacing and letter spacing like if you want to give a space
between two words then you can use word spacing if you want to give space between two letters you
can use letter spacings okay and there is something also called as line height line height is used to
adjust this one height like what are the heights like let's say if i give uh i'll show you the
difference since it's a paragraph we have yeah line spacing
uh it's a line height guys let's say if i give eight pixel
okay let's say i give uh 20 pixel let's say 25 pixel for the space now what do you see this what
what do you understand like if you see uh like if i let's say i go to the chrome now since line height
is 25 now if you see here what i applied here uh let's not refresh let me refresh this one
okay i didn't save it let's save it come back here this is an element selector guys i use
this element selector i hover over this and i click on this so it takes me to that paragraph
and i can see here what are the styles are applying now on the paragraph if you see line
height 25 pixel is there now if i keep on increasing if you see the each line right uh
the under the paragraph let's say a paragraph is having a five six lines of paragraph now we are
deciding what would be the size of each line if you see there are books which have bigger lines
divided blocks such that in early age when you write down like if you remember hindi sort of
whenever you write a hindi language you learn you have a different sort of lines distributed book
when you go for english you have a rule book of different lines right so that way each line
can have a certain space that depending on that we can customize it okay
can you show where and how you increase that okay now if you see okay if it is not visible
give me a second can you see this now uh shan if you see i selected element selector then i select
this content now if you see in the style block right i have this line height now line height is
usually used for each row height what is the row of each each row height if i reduce it it will
both will collide or else i can increase it which will give me a spacing between two lines like how
much spacing do i need between lines okay so i hope these three things are clear one is word
spacing how much space you need between words and then there is something called letter spacing how
much space you need between the letters and then there is space between lines how many how much
space you need this between the lines i i hope these properties are clear to all like can you
give me thumbs up if this properties are clear related to font i see three good good guys thank
you so i'll try to summarize here what all things that we have learned okay so related to
font something that we have seen in last classes field called font family which is used to you know
add different type of uh font like text like font which are handling like maybe calligraphy or
chinese or any sort of things like different types of fonts that you see something in newspaper or
same language but writing it in a different way okay then we have discussed something called font
size which is used to increase the size of like letters how much uh size you want to see okay
again it has all the things large larger smaller bold like and pixels it takes and every other
different unity it takes okay then we have discussed something called font weight which
is used to handle boldness like how much bold content you need it then something we discussed
about is text align right then we have discussed something called as text decoration which is used
to add underscores are or like you know line through i mean scratch the line or get underscore
on the top right then we have discussed three types of spacing between like words
word spacing
then we had letter spacing
then something called as line height
i hope this this whatever words you have seen now all this you are familiar now you would be
familiar with it like if you see if you want to use it in future you will be able to use them
right a basic idea that you have it in your mind right
great guys now
thank you
now we'll start with some of the some of them in one of the important topic of css actually
okay which is called box model
okay but before coming to box model let's take off one example okay let's take this one example
that uh have anyone been to vilas like have anyone seen vilas society
like a society filled with vilas or anyone seen in movies or
you know so like what we say series says
open there i'll share you the links you click you can go through them
okay for the like all the attributes are the properties for each one right
well i'll share you all these things you can refer to them okay now so has everyone seen it
firstly let's say there is something like this is an villa
uh consider and hot sort of villa guys okay but now each villa uh has some specialty like
uh around the villa what do you usually see guys
some carpet area filled of gardens right can you imagine right now let's say i have this
now let's say i have this
let's say this is a garden i'll pick some other color okay this is a garden area right
where you have plantation also you have a pathway right a pathway to the home but there is something
like garden now after that garden then do you think uh the other home the other building right
let's say if i draw again other building other house will be attached to this one or there will
be a space let's say if i if i want to create a new building here it would be attached to this
border or there will be some space space right let's say i do the same thing
let's say i design other two villas let's say i keep it this way
okay now so what we have seen here is that firstly
let's say i go to a house there is something like a house area right let's say i if i write
down the architectural part there is a house area where you can stay
right outside house area then there is something like garden area
right then there is a boundary wall right
right
once your boundary wall is done then you have something like called as space empty space
let's say empty space
which is like mandatory or i have seen people fighting for this space right if someone attaches
their building for this one there are too many fights mandatory
empty space right so overall overall this is how things look like right house structure or
something like now right this is how a generally a house looks like now each element in html is
also same i know you won't believe it but each html element is also you can consider it as a villa
okay now let's talk about it when i say each element is a villa itself now what do i exactly
mean by that is now if you are writing something in the paragraph content or between a heading
content anything that you write in between those elements each elements each tags okay
will have the same properties you can define them now let's say you have
told like let's say this is a content area again i'm talking in terms of now html okay
this is content area
around that content area as you need a garden you have something called as padding
okay padding is you can say the gardens for the the html elements you added after that
you need a border or a fencing okay this is something called as border
border okay you can say a border then you have something called
margin
okay margin is something which keeps space between two of the content like if you go and see
in any textbooks or anything a each paragraph have a some space around it right that thing is
same thing like these are the three basic things that you can relate with box model when you go
for box model we are talking about only three properties okay those are margin
padding and border
okay i hope these three things are not like new to new to you now you are able to understand
or relate with this one right with this example i'll show you the real time application of this
one but now let's see the content that we have already prepared right now i'll go to the example
of fonts that we have used now let's say i go to this paragraph now do you see this paragraph the
if i highlight our paragraph the yellow line the yellow everyone can see that
yellow line before over the lorem right
right now let's see what that yellow line is about so where you can see the box model
once you expand this tab and you go to the bottom in the style now if you see
there is something called margin border and padding and the content area the content area
is the height and width of the content that you see let's say if i highlight over it if you see
this is the content area or you can say the area of that particular house that needs
fine we told that hey this content doesn't need any garden or it doesn't need border
but it surely need margin on the top and bottom so what it says that before the next line content
or the earlier content whatever the this is heading right the content it should be separated
i need a space between the each of the houses so that each of the space between each of houses
is decided by margin if you want to add a garden around it let's say if i go to the padding let's
say i go and select here and i want to add a like padding on the top side i can give 20 as as soon
as i enter see this what's happened on the this highlighted one so as soon as i click enter now
if you see there's something called green space added which is like what what do i exactly mean
by that is like i've added a garden let's say if i want to add a garden on left side okay which is
15 right now if you see that content moved it so are you able to relate like how this thing works
guys are you able to relate the box model now better
it is that is it guys like how each element in the html i've shown with a p tag now if you go
and go and select the h1 tag also it will also have that same box model so all the properties
in html everything that you have it you can define three properties to it which are padding margin
three properties to it which are padding margin and border to it everything is a box in a html
so now let's do one thing let's do one thing we'll go and do some of the you know we'll build some
boxes and we'll see how how uh you can build actually how can you apply this all this fields
okay let me go here and create one new folder called box model
okay inside this i'll create new file called index.html let's say i have html5
and i say this as a box model
okay so what we'll do it here is simply i'll copy some content for you don't need it actually
can type it let's say this is a div okay inside this let's say i say there's a paragraph i say this is
a scalar class simply okay now i'll go to the style block let's say i open this in the view
you can see this is a scalar class is something coming already now what we'll do is like let's
say i go to this style block
and i select this particular p tag so let's say i give a class as scalar class
name let's i minimize this one and i go into style block for selecting class how can i select
this class selector is how can i write it using dot operator right it's a scalar class
now let's say first what we want to do is let's say we want to have some border let's say we want
to have border now if i go and write border okay so border has again three list of properties guys
okay you can define how many pixels border you need let's say you have two pixel of border
okay now the solid and the color which selects is like let's say i select this one then you go for
border style okay let's say i go for border style here border style is like something some
some peoples have fencing with current something some people have small walls some have big walls
some have big walls right similarly in html elements also you can have different types of
borders like you can have dashed line or you can have dotted lines around it
or else you can also have solid which is like single line then you can also have border color
to it okay when you go for border color let's say i select as brown
okay i hope this property is clear now what happens is we can write all these things into
together into one line now if i define a border i can say two pixel solid brown this is what i
was doing it earlier like i was combining border border style and color is this clear guys
i hope this border property is clear like how we can leverage how we can add it
now once border is done so each thing right as i've told you earlier if you see in the box
you can have each customized let's say now when i'm applying border to pixel right what's happening is
on top bottom left right two pixel is being applied but if i want to change it on a top and
bottom how can i do it is that let's say border i can say top okay i can say border top and i can
say 10 pixel solid brown if you see what i exactly doing is like if you want to customize like here
all the fields are different different like you can apply for left right bottom top or anything
that you want to have right customizable any way that you can have it okay now even you can add it
for border border bottom let's say you go for eight pixel solid brown
okay you might have seen many rajinikanth movies right where his name comes in between top border
and bottom borders are thick lines which comes like left to right in a low lines or in old movies
you can see right so this is how you can what about border size yeah this is a border size right 10
yeah this is a border size right 10 pixel 8 pixel on the sides also you can do
border left you can apply left and right also you have left right and everything you can define it
clear you can also do one thing let's say let's say you i want to comment this thing
let's say i want to comment this thing i say 10 pixel
okay for border you have to individually define it let's say i comment this one also uh i keep this
open
okay i keep this comment border then i say 10 pixel 5 pixel 3 pixel then 2 pixel
no it's not working for the border but border is something simply you can apply
uh like how much you need it i hope this this properties are clear guys how this thing works
how border you can apply it and how we can deal with this like there are three properties you
deal generally apply one is but the the size of the border then the style and the color
then there is something like border radius when you select border radius you can select
how much curvature you need on the edges let's say if i give 8 pixel okay if i give 8 pixel
now do you see this this is like a bit curved this looks like bit curved like the buttons are
that are built these days like curved buttons okay so border radius is generally used for this one
mostly images right uh what if you see the pictures like uh in link then you see that
there is a picture in circle right let's say i
i don't have linkedin login here but you can explore linkedin go put a debugger if you give
50 percent right let's say if i give 50 percent you'll see that converts into a circular okay
border it is used to convert that border into sub like depending on the type of items that
you can play around you can give or use this properties okay now moving to the next property
what i'll do is now i'll go and play around with the padding part now let's say i add some padding
okay what i what i'll say is that let's say i give some padding like 10 pixel
now here if you go and see here again the padding is around left right bottom right
right top left right bottom now similarly if you want to give it each side padding you can give
again padding left or padding right or padding bottom everything you can deal with it but what
if you want to define a different heights of padding in a same value you can do it like let's
say i if i give it this way 8 pixel 10 pixel 8 pixel if you see here what's happened is
top and bottom padding are same left and right padding are same now what does exactly mean is
how you how we can define things like this way is that when you
let's say i'll define what is the rule for when you define it all properties in one line
you select first top then bottom then like sorry top right bottom left
does this look like something something is clock right so you have to define properties
in terms of clock right let's say if i give 18 pixel so right property doesn't matter because
if you see if i give let's say this instead of this this is a class if i give lower m 20
if you just see now what will happen if i increase the right if you see right side padding is added
i'll come to that somewhere i'll come to that now if you see what's happening here when i
added pattern let's say if i go and add 20 now bottom padding is increased let's say if i give
50 okay let's similarly let's give 50 here okay this is how you can deal with padding like you
can add it padding across left right bottom and if you want to define let's say you also can do
one thing is that if you want to give it a top and bottom to be same and left right right to be same
then you can what you can do is you can define it in two terms itself let's say i go and say
padding 10 pixel and 8 pixel it will take it as like top and bottom as 10 pixel
and left and right as 8 pixel so the convention for this one goes as top bottom will be same left
right will be same
okay i hope this is clear guys how padding you can define it individually or for one side or
all the sides right if you want to define it like if you're going for in one line it goes in the
clock signal if you are defining like both the sides top and bottom are same left and right are
same you can define it in two ways okay so this is how you can deal with padding now let's say
you also have something like margin to show margin what i'll do is that let's say i create
another paragraph if you see now let's say i open this in a live server too
because i wanted to show you something
do you see space between this each paragraph guys already
do you see space between this paragraph already like this space after border right
where this space yellow space is coming from why this yellow space is coming from where this is
coming from why this yellow space is coming from where this is coming from
this padding margin 16 we haven't given it right have we defined margin 16 for any of the paragraphs
no right so what happens how it happens guys is that you know
mostly div and span are the empty tags that you generally see all other tags are like semantic
tags now each semantic tags build with certain style in html but if you wanted to build it like
a raw you have to define few properties okay have anyone seen many times that on the top of the
project whenever you go and see they add some universal selector does anyone know universal
selector here does anyone know universal selector so what does universal selector is means it means
say that it should apply for the all the properties when i say hash when i say star so it means that
i am applying for the all the properties and whenever you start it is supposed to make
padding equal to zero and margin equal to zero by default so what happens is now let's say now
when i declare padding and margin as zero now if you see all of them have sticked together
i'm just saying that whatever by default your style is there now whatever your default style is
there it don't bring that one i'll define my custom one because my calculation is going wrong
this is point here like how this is working padding and margin
because paragraph by default let's say if i read remove this margin and i save it so if you see
so if you see even though we haven't defined margin by default paragraph tag is bringing
some of the margin along with it so if you want to override and custom make it custom according to us
we can all it is suggested it is a like a good practice that you you know you clear all the
existing margins then only you go and design your custom margins is this clear guys
please
how many of you understand understood this point like why i'm making margin zero
or how many did not understand it okay now going to next point now here
let's say i see one two great okay thank you people i would request you right if you're not
understanding it give me thumbs down instantly no specific no space between the paragraph
no pendra what i'm doing is saying is that let's say this paragraph is a built-in head stream
melting that i'm using it already but what i'm saying is that hey there are some you know they
are bringing some their inlines like styles which are defined by browser itself so whenever i'm
going and saying that hey i'm i'm suddenly seeing that i've designed a paragraph next to each other
i don't know how the space is coming suddenly right how the space is coming we are we haven't
defined that space right so i'm saying that to overcome this come of shortcomings right
because i'm showing you simple structure here that's why you don't find a problem
but imagine you are building a big scale project and let's say you defined like content
or let's say netflix dashboard right there are images cards side on side if there is a space by
default is coming because of in built-in html elements that is not right right you want to
override as per your need so what it is generally suggested is that if there are some whatever
html elements since every html element is a box in nature all the html elements will have certain
styles attached with it so what we say that hey don't give me those styles bring all the properties
whatever you have but give me mad padding and margin as zero so we are overriding at the start
and applying for every html element on the top i hope this is clear guys to abhinav and hariprasad
also
cool now once once this is done so we remove for all the elements yeah so we are
yeah overriding for removing for all the elements right now i have some mathematical question guys
now tell me the height of this each box now what would be the height and width of this each box
what would be the height of this box
what would be the general formula of this height and width how would you calculate
you have you can see 37 pixel
okay
yeah
sheik has suggested that content plus padding plus border open says that margin padding border
and 37 pixel so in general whenever you go for height and width right whenever you go for height
and width of a particular html element something like if you go for height it would be like
content area or html element like 37 pixel we had plus padding on y-axis
plus border
on y-axis plus margin on y-axis
similarly for width
width content area width
plus padding x
plus border x
plus margin x right do you guys agree this actual height and actual width would be this is the
summation of this one can you guys give me thumbs up guys quick thumbs up if you are
able to agree with this point because the other element will start after only this and height
and width is consumed right now if you go and see the height of this particular element is like
37 pixel plus 10 plus 10 plus 2 plus 2 right 20 plus now if you see 37 plus 20 plus 2 4
57 plus 4 61 right the height would be 61 right
do you guys agree the height would be 61 now let's say i also add margin for for the space
right i override it let's say i also add margin now margin let's say 5 pixel i added 5 pixel margin
around okay now if i do it 5 pixel 61 plus 10 which is 71 is height now but
do you see any problem this way like if you are saying that hey uh like whatever you are adding
all of those things and consuming that space but what if i want you to consume only 37 pixel of
height and you can deduct whatever padding height border and margin from inside that because if you
go uh go and buy a property or a villa right they'll give you a complete space in that only
you have to content area space will be given like whole villa space would be given inside that only
you should have uh like padding border right do you guys agree like they wouldn't you be giving
extra space for you right for you can have garden you can have also border how many ways you want
you can build it it doesn't work that way right so for that one let's say if you want the formula
the currently we have discussed this one if you want this formula to work this way let's say
this is default in nature whatever we have discussed this is default in nature but if
we want this to work such way that height is equal to content area
uh minus padding of y
minus border of y margin of y
i mean uh this would actually result
this would actually equal to the content height
right let's say i replace this one with content instead of content area height
whatever height is defined by you isn't it
so if you want this thing to work this way if you want this work to this if you want your
html environment to work this way right there's a one property that you add globally that is called
as border box
give me a second guys
sorry box sizing
these are one-time elements guys if you see when i when you click border box
it changes nothing seems to be changing but if you go and see here below let me refresh it
now give me a second
let me to cut this here and apply it for the body
uh
i didn't yet apply it
give me a second okay i have to go for custom element not for the whole element uh let's say
if i want to go and apply for the scalar classes let's say i go and uh do it for here when i apply
it here now even then it's not changing
but if i go and let's say okay if we haven't defined height here actually
we have to define height to see the changes here let's say i go and define height 200 pixel firstly
okay now
now if you see here what just happened here uh let me make it 100 guys uh for a sec now how this
formula will work now i've gave paragraph height as 100 pixel if you see on the top 100 pixel
but the content area space whichever this content area space is made into 76
how it is coming up to 76 because it detected the space for padding border and margin
this is the same way how this formula that i've just wrote it like height whatever you define
height for each html element if you want that to consume only that amount of height let's say
you you say that hey my height of the box is 100 but if you don't say box box sizing as border
box now let's see how this behaves the height of the box ultimately become 100 plus 20 plus 4
which is 124 plus 10 134 but we said that box should be size of only 100
okay if you want to that stick all those sizes heights to be that same thing right then you
have to go and use this property as box sizing as border box is this point clear guys how that box
sizing is helping us
anyone did like anyone having any doubts here
i see two people thumbs down cool further three guys please vote it so that i am
you are not getting it okay cool okay fine let's say going back and taking this example
okay
let's say your villas dimensions
is width into height or height into width let's say i gave width as 200 pixel and height as 100
pixel right if i've given this height and width of your dimensions of villa now you are supposed
to add garden border inside this one itself right leave it extra space now this is a box
leave it this extra space but this till this border is supposed to be in 100 percent 100
pixel height itself right now so that is what i'm saying now whenever you go by default html
right what happens is whenever you say that hey height should be 100 pixel
and padding should be
10 pixel and margin should be sorry border should be
5 pixel then this is like going on top and bottom so it will be 20 pixel this is also
going on top and bottom so it this will be 10 pixel now the total height of actual building
is calculated as 120 plus 10 130 pixel but do you have 130 pixel of size available according
but do you have 130 pixel of size available according to your plot you have only 100 pixel right
if you construct an extra if you take an extra space and construct it
they'll come municipality will come and demolish your house right or that society will fight with
you so that is what happening here if you see if i go and say let's say this is my house
okay i will remove this box sizing and if you see i didn't save it now
save it now if you see i've told that hey my house size is 100 height but i'm adding a garden plus
border to it now the what what is happening it is increasing the height of that whole house
because we are adding garden and borders to it but we don't want it we want something that
hey let's say i'm having garden of 10 pixel on top and bottom then i would say that if i remove
this i'll have only for the house i'll have only 70 pixel height left right this is how it should
be now if i'm having actual house i'm building it height content or house height
should be 70 pixel then padding should be
20 since i'm considering top and bottom top 10 bottom 10 border should be top and bottom 10 pixel
is this clear now like this example is clear at least
guys who people who gave me thumbs down so i would i'm asking you them so it's this example
that i'm not going into html part as of now i'm just explaining this mathematical thing now this
is by default nature this is the default nature whatever you give height padding and border it
will be added as extra but if you want this sort of calculation to work which is actually right
according to our rules of understanding with real life then you are supposed to use something
called as border box sorry box sizing as border box
when i say border box i mean to say that whole like include whole till till the border area
okay now let's go and see what's happening when i don't apply box sizing property my height becomes
100 plus 20 plus 4 124 it becomes what if i go and apply this property what if i go and apply
this property what if i go and apply this property i come back and i see
that it becomes 76 plus 20 which is 96 plus 400 is this clear what problem this box sizing is
solving for us uh guys if there are still someone who don't understand it please give
me thumbs up thumbs down that works for me i can re-explain this topic
okay it's just that if you are still facing challenge i would request you to watch the
video you'll be able to get it completely is it automatically yeah it is automatically adjusting
on kids so it is fixing it okay i'm just adding one property i'm saying it that the height of
the whole box should be only maximum 100 pixel now if you want margin like padding and border
you would deduct it from inside that let's say if i make five five pixel of border and i save it if
you go and see here my height of border earlier it was 76 now it became 70 only it won't include
margin shake so margin is separate if i made it return that way i'll clean it up margin formula
okay it won't include margin it would include only these three parts okay let me make this part
also clear okay margin is separately because the space will be given by society only yeah it will
adjust calculations automatically but the default value for box sizing is content box if you again
box sizing is content box if you again convert into content box right
the box will be size of 100 these are extra added again 10 and uh extra 10
if you you can always fix this using border box
okay i hope this box sizing property is clear now
uh so how many of you are clear with this like properties like why we made padding margin zero
and what this property is making so generally these three fields right if i take it on this one
these three fields are by default every project they certainly add these things like margin
padding and box sizing because they assume that they will define for everything what they need it
it doesn't want it they don't want system to bring anything their sizes or anything
we'll define it our own okay i hope uh all this current topics that we have discussed are clear
guys like related to box model or like uh you know the padding margin all of these three properties
i hope everyone is clear anyone having still doubts please let me know uh or else i'll start
one quiz for you okay so so one simple quiz guys uh try to attempt it i'm starting it
so
take your time guys uh time is there
okay
i see only 22 people voted in uh people uh i have seen many people are there in class guys try to
mark your vote
mark your option actually
come on guys
okay so i'm ending the quiz guys so i've seen 28 people have voted in and out of that 75 people
have said right answer so actually when i've told you already right the property is here itself you
can see on the uh like samvith has answered in very quick time right so we have already discussed
like if you want to add margin or padding you can add it in terms of clock size like top right
top right bottom left so if you if you want to add respective you know sizes of
padding or margin to it okay i hope uh this thing is clear guys like how
this thing uh like box model and font text area related content till now so this is clear
we'll go ahead with one of the next content of today's class which is display property
okay from now on guys uh these have been uh display property has been simple i would say
that we have we already know that uh what does display do okay uh pretty simple
okay let's say i go and design index start html i have okay let's have go for display property
and i have div tag inside that again i have div tag let's say i have one this i have four elements to it
say i have something like two three and four and let's say this is something like class container
okay and let's say these are class like items
okay uh so i'm making it preview
okay now let's say i have some default styles i added to
container let's say selecting a container class since we have introduced all the properties i'll
try to write it down such that you know we are hands-on with them firstly i'll go and make the
j star
margin to be zero pixel and padding to be zero pixel now as soon as i do this guys
just see what's happening and
box sizing
okay now once i have been this we have done this what i'll do is like let's say i have this div
container so i'll have some certain height and width to it let's say 300 pixel to it and width
should be 300 pixel and let's say we have some border to it i say five pixels solid or let's say
dotted and gray okay uh doesn't look good so solid okay now once we have added this let's
say we also have some padding let's say we say 10 pixel around each element
and margin should be 20 pixel from each side okay this is something we have already discussed
till now uh nothing new i'm just applying those properties so that we get used to it so can we
align them in single line each is it in the box yeah that is where i'm coming okay no no
which type of these elements are like which category this elements comes in dips i have
seen discussed this one already whether this is an inline element or this is an block element guys
block element right now block elements always starts in new line and uh like we said that item
one item two item three item four it's it's always starting in new line but what if we want to
convert them into inline element what if we want them to come side by side as just ankit mentioned
them to come side by side as just ankit mentioned
so there those sort of places itself we use property called as display display property
is used to deal with these items to convert them into uh different types of like you know display
to uh like inline to block block to inline let's say i go and say item display to inline
okay as soon as i do this i add dot now if you see this these are converted into
uh not flexed some with yet don't let's not go there yet okay let's pick to fix to display
can you see this ankit your problem is solved as soon as i told it that uh you know item should
be converted into inline now what if what is the one property that inline elements we cannot
apply to like what if we want can we can we apply width and height to this one guys
can we apply width and height to inline elements
let's say i apply 25 pixel let's say i apply height to be 20 pixel and let's say i also have
a border uh five pixel solid pink let's say i make it three and i also have some padding to it
five pixel around it okay also let's say i gave some margin to it
10 pixel but do you see any height and width are getting affected let's say i make for
100 also not being applied right no heights are see height and width are generally not applied
for inline elements that is what we have discussed earlier when i have told you about font text when
we discuss related to this example right what is the difference between span and h1 and p tag same
same example right same example we picked it up like text align center is not happening because
it can it takes only the space it needed you cannot deal with it you cannot add extra height
and width to it but what if i comment this one what if i comment this one
would the width and height would be applied
right
that's right let's see this if i apply this if you see
let's say i make this as container height as 100 percent 100 percent
100 percent okay this can you see this let's say i make in terms of percentages uh 10 percent
and let's say this is 20 percent right and let's say width would be 60 percent of it
just to view it now i hope they are able to get it like what is our difference between
inline and block and how can you convert an inline element into block block and inline let's say i
have a span text now i'll have next items as a span okay let's say these are the span text
uh let me repeat a span okay five six seven eight okay i'll have a class here
which will say span item or let's say this is uh item one
these are spanned by default the nature of this one is like if we want to convert them into a
block how would we do this as you should help me out uh with this example because
i have solved for one thing you have to suggest me take how can i make them same as this one let's
say we apply all of these properties right by default we know that height and width wouldn't
be applied display equal to block right let's see if i see this now this is working fine right
right now but what i'm saying is that what i'm saying is that now let's say i converted into
this one as a uh six and six i'm figuring this one
so i hope this is clear like how item can be converted to block block to inline inline to block
this is clear to everyone guys final thumbs up i will shoot next question
okay now let's say next element next thing that i have is uh okay which should be more
uh let's say i save 10 let's say make it 15
okay fine what my question is i want to align them in a single row i want to align them in
a single row all of these items and apply height and width through it how can how can i do it
so there are div elements there are span elements i want to apply
let's say let's solve for first four elements first four elements let's solve problem for
first four elements let's say we have item one two and three four uh no we don't want
to use display flex hashvini here so dhira suggest inline block how many of you think
that inline block in inline block would solve the problem
i see one thumbs up
uh if you don't know if you're not sure you can give me a thumbs down if you're not sure
but i just want to know you all of you got the question right all of you got the question
right i just want to convert them into horizontal row but i also want them to have height and width
so guys what we can do is that if you want to convert any element into let's say inline
you converted into inline they are fine but if you want to apply height and width to it
you can always use something called inline block when you use inline block right it is supposed to
take the height and width whatever you mention it is that clear guys whenever you apply inline block
all the elements inside it would be converted into inline but you can apply height and width
converted into inline but you can apply height and width to it that's only the difference
okay the difference between inline and block we know but if we convert something into inline block
we are converting such that those are aligned in horizontal line and it is taking only the
amount of space it needs right we can apply height and width to those particular elements clear
okay now can you see this like all the boxes are arranged in a right like a let's say if i have a
nine element so i have a nine element this is looking like a dialer if i reduce the
right
let's say whatever it is so i hope a difference between let's let's say i write it down on the
ipad so that it's a kind of a revision so we know that there are some elements let's say we are
taking something like inline block and inline block
something like inline block and inline block
right if i write down definition takes only the space needed
right
height and width not applied
but when it comes to block
takes whole row
new row to render data
and height and width
can be applied
applied
when it comes to inline block we say that takes only the space needed
and also
we can apply height and width
right these are the basic differences guys is everyone aligned with this
between inline block and inline block
okay if everyone is aligned with this i have another thing to show you guys okay
then there is another property called
display none what does it do display none anyone any idea display none
let's say if i make it none
you see this all the items been removed nothing will display but there is something called also
display hidden
sorry display none is a one property i can also achieve this using
visibility hidden what would be the difference between these two guys
like both are achieving same thing right both are achieving same thing firstly
let's say i make it display none you see we are not able to see elements if i comment this and
uncomment this one still the same thing right
so people are saying the space will be there space will be affected okay display equal to none what
will happen think in terms of answer in terms of dom guys let's say i open this in live server
give me a second
let's say i open this in live server give me a second
in terms of dom guys let's say i open this in live server give me a second
okay okay there are too many answers but let's say i go to inspect
i select inspect selector i just hit here this is a container that we have written now if you see
what is the property that we applied on item one we say that visibility hidden when visibility
hidden like if you see i'm hovering over this property i can see those boxes right actually
but it is like present here present in the dom but what if i uncomment this one and i make this one
okay still it are present in dom firstly okay some people confuse you with this question firstly
like whether the elements are removed from the dom or those are there first question is this one
second thing goes for the space when you can see about the space when you can see the problem
about the space is when you have extra elements below firstly let's say i go and add
why that issue why that question of item element is present in dom or not comes is i'll tell you
let's say i go and add 10 okay now if you see 10 is there but where you can see the 10
it is below the 3 whereas it's supposed to be after 4 isn't it
isn't it
because we defined after 4 right it is after 4 directly because these elements are removed
if these elements are removed after 4 the 10 should be there right but 10 is coming
here at the edge the reason for this one is because for the visibility hidden
then all the properties which are defined only they are hidden but not removed
is this clear for visibility the items are hidden but not removed like there is a box
you just throw a cloth on it but there is a box under the cloth but when it comes to display equal
to none the boxes are removed itself so when the people say that display equal to none do you think
the items are not removed i mean items are present in dom they ask this question
because if you see in the dom still you have these elements present you can still play around with
them isn't it so remember with this only one thing as you said that space will affect it that is all
good but related to dom also remember this point okay i hope this is clear guys how visibility and
display works now when you define both the properties display is overriding the visibility
okay can you repeat from the point of dom okay so what i was saying is that sambit here
like this though i haven't introduced the word dom like it's a just a document object model
which represents a tree tree like data structure builds a whole like a tree we'll see it in the
javascript initial class but here this is what a representation of dom looks like all the html
in the element tag what's happening is when i'm using display equal to none right because when
i'm display equal to none the element 10 is coming exactly after the four it means that all the
elements are removed from that space right that that items are not there itself there's a difference
between hiding and removing it so display equal to none works as something that removed it so when
we are removing it we mean to say that those are shouldn't be present even if you consider a tree
even if you consider a tree if you have a nodes of 10 nodes if you say that display none for the
some five four nodes it means that we are removing that nodes right but remember that it present in
the dom in both the cases okay only something like the behavior how display equal to none and
visibility hidden is working hiding and removing kind of that okay so let me say this one
uh
display none
removes elements
from screen you can say this way whereas visibility hidden
takes space and hide the elements
okay so i hope these points are clear guys how visibility and display none works
so i'm converting this into display equal to inline block for our sake
okay so even with the display none the elements will be present in dom yeah that's what it is
looking like right that's what it is showing here you can still see that the element here it is there
like let's say i use display none right okay i remove this one if you see i'm hovering over it
but it's not present in the element but they are present in the dom tree right
they're not on the hd document but they're present in the dom tree
that is what i was talking about shape right so i mean they try to confuse your test they
basically all the answers that you gave were right that uh here the space will get affected
or there will be some items where hidden or removed but i want to say that hey
yeah dom will not be affected in general dom will be there okay
okay so if this is this thing is clear display property is also completed okay i hope this
things are clear if you need break let me know how many minutes you need it because i have one of
the important property to cover uh which is a position where i've seen people been asking me
from the first class about the position which is like difficult one we'll come back and we'll
discuss on a position property you need 10 minutes okay i'll keep 10 minutes but as i need your full
attention after uh 10 minutes okay because that's a one of the uh important topic an easier topic
to say so this push the code yeah okay i'll do that uh give me a second i'll push the code
so
uh done some bit okay i'm starting 10 minutes guys uh so please uh come back with full energy
because i need uh you to understand that topic well okay because that is somewhere people
try to struggle and it has been asked in interviews also
which software i'm using to teach uh which one ankit i'll start the timer i can discuss with you
guys take the brick uh html this one uh this one is vs code
okay visual studio code if you go to the project repo right uh you go to self-study link uh let's
say i show it in the pre-open and preview i've given this uh vs code editor download link also
you can download it from here okay and also uh if you want uh live server i've given that and all
the reference material whatever you need to go through i'm giving in self-study document you can
refer to that class by class okay i'll keep on adding the document that you have to go through
after each class because all the things cannot be thought or i cannot go in depth because i have the
time like time right that two and a half hours three hours whatever it is so if you read more
you can come back and we can discuss in depth more if you have those questions
okay so guys take the break i'll come in a minute
you
guys i hope everyone is back
guys can you give me some reactions uh if you're back
okay thank you thank you i see six people
so guys what we have discussed till now font text
then we discussed box model
then we discussed display on top level we discussed all the types of things that
that you can do here we learned margin padding and border and box sizing
property right in display we have understood in line in line block then
lock then none and visibility right hidden so I hope when you see this
property is whatever I've just wrote now everything is clear to you right
anything do you feel like still new to you or anything you feel under
confident about any property let me know if I write down font size weight text
decoration spacing all type of spacing right guys are you confident about this
properties we discussed give me thumbs up if you are feeling confident about
this one or like from concept point like I don't assume that you are expert at
them because it will come with practice but you understand them right I see six
thumbs up okay if I'm not getting thumbs down I'll agree I'll consider that you
had a good understanding on them okay moving it this to the property one of
the confusing property is position how many you have faced under problem
understanding this one if you have studied earlier if you have studied
early how many of you have faced challenge understanding this one three
people okay okay okay cool no worries I see three people no yes when I say when
I say this position at office what do you exactly know about it like position
at office let's say I'm sd2 I'm sd2 what would be the role like sd1 then I can go
to sd3 or senior software then maybe at my office we call it as MTS one which
is tough right this is the hierarchy right we say this one as a position only
know in in general terms which keeps changing with your experience and your
performance right do you guys agree like what's your position at your office
not a multitasking the member of technical stuff they call it as a staff
engineer they were working in on actually you know renaming this
convention also but this is what position looks like right similarly if
you go for this one also we have said that all the elements are like boxes
HTML elements are like boxes now all this boxes whatever boxes are there are
present in one of the box which is your laptop or your device or whatever it is
take right what does whatever the size of your screen is that is a one big box
inside the box box only all the boxes are designed and kept right but if let's
say this is how we design that one to nine inline block one item then what if
we want to move this elements to any side from their respective position
right let's say my phone is currently here if I want to move it from position
that's a left right or top bottom on to the table from its particular position I
can use this property called position okay so position property generally
allows you to move the elements from its designed place place like when I say
design place all the elements whatever we have defined like item one two three
four are designed to be this way side by side but if we want to move from their
position to some other position or like move from with respect to anything if
you are moving them any side if you want to move them any only different places
then we have to go to the position property at least this thing is clear
when to use position and what is position
guys give me some reactions if not if not give me thumbs down if you don't if
you're not getting it give me thumbs down that's okay I'll take it slow okay
I see one thumbs down cool now what do I exactly mean to say is that when I say
HTM element I'll have div one right and div two I'm supposed to render one and
two on the screen right this is a screen right the person Ankit do you agree this
is how it will render right on screen but what if I want to move let's say one
and two here or one is somewhere here and two is still here like this thing
moving the particular element from their respective position though the
dom will be represented this way itself you got this if I have to move that
element to the left right top bottom then I have to approach for this person
position from their respective position like whatever these are position are
default positions okay the default the default there's a one property all the
elements whichever has same element you see the default property is static being
applied to it already whenever I say static what do we mean a difference
between like if you go for physics also static and dynamic right static is
someone who's to who is residing there itself right is not in motion is not
moving anywhere right stable there itself bodies at rest so all the elements
which are like already which are defined in HTML all the that you do it the items
will be defined till now whatever HTML we have written all the elements are by
default are having position static which means that they are not moving from
their position not moving from the question it means whatever you are
defined by default those are applied is this clear guys
till now the whatever story I explained is it clear to everyone right now if we
want them to be dynamic if we want them to dynamic or move from their position
whatever position is like assigned by Dom to them render while rendering we
want to move them and behave in certain way then we go for a properties like
relative absolute then fixed and sticky okay what all these properties are doing
you know one property should be actually enough to move the element like to move
the element you generally use something like top bottom left right again this
all the properties takes values in pixels REM and EM so I haven't discussed
this too I'll discuss in future but current currently consider pixels okay
these are the properties you can define once you define any position this one
this one or this one or this one or anything you are using okay but I hope
position static is clear by default it is rest that's a default nature and it
keeps the values in the same way but when it comes to other things let's say
relative and absolute let's pick them first okay this is somewhere people
confused relative and absolute okay we'll discuss this first now both things
are helpful to move the element from one position to other position from their
assigned well assigned place let's say this is a table and my phone is here
okay what I'm doing is I'm moving my phone from here to here okay I'll say
that this is a distance X and I'll say that this is a distance Y okay what is
happening here which I also make a dotted line I moved my mobile from there
to here now what is generally happening is like if my phone is moving with
respect to its original position like what do I say when I say X X is a
distance which is moving with respect to
original question I mean if I say an element let's say my phone is here let's
say my phone is here at this particular question and I say I'm moving this mobile
to this one this thing can be only done like we are moving it from the
particular question where it was there let's say you say 10 pixel move towards
the right from your point of view left if I'm moving 10 pixel this side I mean
to say that I'm moving it from with respect to its actual original position
and when you can apply this thing when position is relative
but when this role of Y comes role of Y comes when item is moved with respect to
window or you can say table top corner
this is clear guys what I'm denoting X&Y top left yeah top left so I'll show you
this examples both again I'll come back to this example but but how many of you
got this diagram or representation that I was trying to explain if you didn't
get it that's also fine give me thumbs down if you didn't get it I'll explain
with a real-time example then I'll come back okay see too cool further yeah three
people got it no this case let's come back let's do some coding and then come
back so let's say let's create a folder calling as position again inside this
I'll use index start HTML okay let's see the magic is what's happening now I'll
close this I'll render this don't need a server live server but there is nothing
in it yet but let's say this is absolute
versus related okay but before that what I'll do is that let's say I go and define
let's say I have a paragraph I use lorem 20 lorem 5 that's enough again I'll replicate
this one multiple times let's say okay and I say this as class first I use
class as second as third classes second third fourth okay now what I'm doing
here is like I'll create a style block now let's say I created a style block
and I'm just trying to access first element and even if I give display first static okay I'm
giving static okay and if I'm trying to define this property top 10 pixel or bottom 10 pixel
or left 10 pixel actually one of the set of the properties would be enough either
you pick top or bottom and right or a top and left anything would be enough for you
to align the item let's say I'm doing it this way nothing is being applied firstly do you
guys agree I made this change I applied to this first class do you see when I make it
static and I'm trying to apply this property this top bottom left right first those are not
applying to it is this clear because static property doesn't take any changes along with it
it doesn't move the element from its position it keeps it static okay now let's say I'm making
it relative okay sorry I have to pardon me is no one reminded me I have to make position static
I went on to define as display again but I'm I want to reconfirm that nothing is changing okay
let's say I comment this and I make it relative okay still there is no change in this lore but
what if I make this particular thing here do you see there's something happened to it let's say
I create a border of one pixel solid black okay I'll give a color of red so that you can see if
I comment this now let's say there's a particular position this particular red one is already
present what I'm saying is that what if I want to move from that particular position to below
then I can say move it from below 10 10 pixel if I say top equal to 10 pixel so I'm saying it
now wherever it is actual position is there move it 10 pixel below is that clear let's say I open
this I'll show it in the browser I want to explain you basic difference how actually absolute
and relative works firstly if you see I am selecting the element selector okay if you
select this one if I remove this if you say it is going to that actual position from its wherever
it is actual position where it should be residing but as soon as I apply this one it is moving
towards below and if I give let's say left value let's say I give left 10 pixel now can you see
this it is moving from that particular position to left to the towards moving towards left I'm
going towards right yes how many of you understand how relative works it is actually moving from
its X its position itself like if you see that diagram right whatever I was saying so whatever's
definition I'm so like my mobile was here not this one but I don't know which yeah this one
let's say this was a position I moved it to this position that's I said left equal to 10 pixel when
I'm moving with actual its respective post position which was actual position not horizontal axis
somebody don't take it that mode towards left yeah so from its actual position wherever it
was residing I'm moving from there okay but what if I make now let's see what if I make this
particular value I remove this and I make it absolute do you see one thing something happened
guys do you see something I had four content here I had four content and the values got merged do
you see you can see only three things there what if I make color to be blue okay and I go and add
let's say top 10 pixel or let's say 20 pixel can you see what happened here guys
how many of you understood what happened here so what I said earlier from diagram
let's say item is moved with respect to window like top left corner I mean to say that it will
start whenever you define it absolute right so that particular position wherever that item is
there it will be removed pulled up from there it will be taken to the starting position let's say
I don't want to deal with the first item okay let's say I don't want to deal with the first
item I'll select the fourth item itself if you are confused about first item that's I select the
fourth item no okay so fourth item it is relative let's make absolute do you guys agree now even
the fourth item was pulled and took to we took it to the first position top most position top most
like windows position and from there we are moving it wherever position we want to now is
the difference is clear guys what does relative and what is absolute absolute always moves from
the window position like whatever top left right bottom you give it moves with respect to that
window position whereas relative takes from its actual position where it was earlier there from
there will move left and right and bottom this is basic difference clear guys how many of you
have understood this one if there is still someone who didn't understand let me know because the
only difference between absolute and relative is this one I see one thumbs down do you want
me to unmute you some bit you want me to unmute you okay okay just recap okay I'll do this one
let's say again re-explaining yeah no matter where it will be pulled it will be pulled it's
like boss I'm I'm the boss of the HTML I don't care I'll be removed from my position I'll go
anywhere I want okay you define me where I want to go using top left right bottom absolute is
that that kind of person is that clear some with okay yeah no then let's say I actually
write down few examples to it it's the same thing guys but what I'm trying to do is that let's say
I copy paste some of the content for you so that you can refer it better okay I made this one but
let's say I have an example I build this again lorem ipsum itself now with let's say what I have
done is I add some styles to this paragraph div container let's say these are the things that
I added nothing just like 5 pixel border and I've given height and width nothing much in it then
we know that static doesn't matter right even if I declare you know here since these are all
paragraphs let's say if I declare p tag and I add it like position static doesn't matter
that should be clear to you okay but I'm removing it then let's say I have here IDs like para 1 para
2 because I have defined it using IDs here let's say I go for para 2 and no if you go in major
websites right major websites like if I go for let's say HDFC life insurance itself life
insurance okay I'll show you one thing here they I won't give my contact details to them
the stuff too much but okay it's very slow isn't it their website is slow or like okay
yeah anyways so what I was what I was trying to show you guys is that let it load
huh now do you see this on top right chat and this one these two things chat with us and this
one these are defined let's say if I go and search in the DOM right I go and search here
in the DOM let's say chat with us if you see this is the class applied message icon okay now if you
go here what they applied here what is the thing applied here what is the position applied here
absolute right and they made something like top zero what is the behavior now if you see if you
want to define a footer for your website this is how you do it you said that hey can you come out
of your actual HTML flow and always stay wherever I define always stay like from top to zero select
like reverse it or else you can also also say this way let's say if I'm this I'm defining a
footer here using para one I can say ID para one I can say position absolute and I also can say
bottom zero okay now if you see this particular thing let's say I define it in the color red
doesn't matter if I have height of let's say 1400 pixel okay you see it is always let me close
this one if you see it will be always there whatever your height of your absolutely like
this one is in the size of it it will be stick to there or else let's say if I make top to be
zero if you see it will go to the top to the particular viewport yeah is this clear guys how
now absolute property works I hope this is clear like how absolute and relative are working now
I'll show you the example of really I'll write down for relative also let's say I have this
styling I've just build this example let's say now if you see para 3 right para 3 I made it
related and I've gave it would be actual position would be this one and the top and left are moving
like from its actual position wherever it was position was this one but I made let's say if
I move again top let's say 20 or 30 its position should be somewhere here but we are moving it
down and also we are moving it from left side we are moving 30 pixel that way okay I hope now
absolute and relative should be clear to you like how they are working okay now I have two
other examples guys they are pretty simple so I'll I'll explain you why pasting it okay because
we are running out of time fixed dot HTML so fixed is like let me show I'll show you with the
example itself that I have let's say I build this HTML 5 and I reclose this one I open show
preview let's say I have a div again I have a list of four paragraphs again I built it using
lorem itself let's say copy and paste it nothing new in this same thing one div as a container
inside that four paragraph with ID para 1 para 2 para 3 para 4 IDs okay and lorem lorem being
added for div what I'll do is like let's say I've added this one inside a style block I'm
adding just for container height and width I'm giving it okay what I did I gave food 400 pixel
okay by default browser will give me a scroller if my page size is more than it is viewport like
my laptop sizes are certain height but if the height is more than my laptop height I'll
automatically get a scroller okay now what I'm going to do is that let's say let's say what
I want to do is like I want this paragraph to be sticked here only like like if you see in the
going back here if this HDFC right the resume application premium the header header part you
can see this this is always stick there can you see this it is always on the top itself it has
hanged but the page is like going below the page is going below once like we are scrolling it okay
so we are saying that hey that position should be fixed when we are getting so that even if the
viewport is changing pages crawling down you want to be something to be fixed you can use
position fixed let's say how can you do it I have para one as an ID para one I use position as
fixed and let's say I define it as top equal to zero okay and I say color equal to right now
though they both are residing if you see even if I'm scrolling it it will be always there the
going it is converted into two layers so the whenever you fix the particular position it
will be always be there now even if you go for bottom right bottom zero okay now whenever I'm
even scrolling it is still stick there the difference between now let me show absolutely
if I open this absolute right index dot HTML show preview okay now if you see this absolutely made
bottom zero if you are scrolling it is coming again it will be only fixing to the viewport I
mean which is using absolute or relative you can make changes till particular viewport only
on current page but if you want to play around with the different level like you you have to
go with fixed one if you want it to be header and footer sort of implementation
here guys can we use both like give me an example some bit like how do you want to use both because
fixed is something in doesn't matter where you give it particular location that hey whether you
fixed has been designed for that use case itself like it will be always stick to the bottom or
top that's how they have used it I hope this thing is clear guys absolute relative and fixed
right now I have the final one let's say I say sticky sticky is really similar to fixed actually
but there's some change in its behavior I will show you how it works left and right can be used
fixed let's say I'll show you it can be used it can be used some bit it can be used just a second
I made some how it can I take your doubt in break we can explore further but I'll complete
the fix sticky part then I'll pick it up okay let's say I open in a show preview no sticky
is actually similar to fixed one but the behavior of sticky starts when it comes to the viewport
I'll show you how let's say this is a sticky and let me copy the this is pretty simple example I
have container and four dips let's say I design container this way using style property okay I
had this dodger blue color and I can do like I may making them all the boxes converted into in line
in line block okay and I've given him height and width okay I don't need this in line block also
okay let it make let it be there so that height and width are applied margin top is applied okay
if you see here what's happening is like I've just made it like I've added margin 300 picture
and given the height and width to the each box nothing new I have done it but there are sometimes
right on the websites right when you're scrolling through there is something right like when you
keep on seeing there is some picture gets stick and if you keep on solving scrolling below but
that they that stick to the viewport there is some picture always stick to the viewport like
there are some advertisements that happens comes let's say there is an overlay overlay comes and
it stick like but the other ones keep scrolling like menu I don't think it I try to find that
example but let's say this is the one even if I scroll I cannot scroll it yeah I'm able to
scroll it but this is not the exactly sticky example nothing is available here as a sticky
even if I go to let's say google news ad okay let's say google news I go to google news
uh use precise location I don't need
okay not now India
let's say I scroll it
there is no behavior as such guys but I'll show you what I exactly mean
okay you will get a sticky ad okay geek for geeks but I hope you got the basic thing now I'll show
you how that actually plays a role okay let's say I select the box three here
box underscore three and I open this and I just add position as sticky so what I'm saying that
box three this particular box should be sticky and I'll give that position let's say top and zero
okay now if you see there's nothing happening but there's nothing happening till that box three
comes as soon as box three comes and goes right even if I'm scrolling box three sticks to the
top position so it behaves like a fixed but only after some extent
only after it reaches the actual viewport it comes into the role
it comes into the role
is that clear guys how sticky is different from
fixed it acts as a fixed only when you get introduced let's say if I make it bottom zero
okay let's say I scroll through if you see
only only like let's say from when you're coming from top three will be there till it's till that
position actual position of three comes okay after that position of three has been entered
it behaves like a normal element goes away but generally this is used for top like as soon as
you've seen that picture it will stick on to the top until even if you scroll it it will stick there
clear so sticky is similar to the fixed type of you know element generally it that comes into
the role whenever you visit that element how you want to behave it okay guys so I hope these are
the basic examples I picked it up if you still have any doubts stay here in the class I'll try
to explain you all those properties like whatever you have doubt what I'll do is like I'll share the
content that you can read through I'll get push the push in the data while you know ping in the
whatsapp group so that you all have the notes okay or wherever you want to refer to okay but
any doubts from today's class if you have please stick to the stick for the doubt session guys
okay uh guys so with your permission can I start doubt session
thank you guys
uh I'm supposed to pick few things uh I have missed it okay some bit has pushed it equation
so normally most of the time I use margin right uh and left to fix the position
is it always recommended to use position uh like as I told you firstly some bit think of this way
uh firstly I'll answer uh some bit question some bit now think of this way the use case right uh
when to go for position I've told you that firstly if I'm moving it from the current position
right I'm moving it from the current position all the other elements are also getting disturbed
okay I'm taking a huge risk that whether I will be able to manage the viewport
or how it will be rendered if you are using position mainly they are dealing with like you
are uh like whatever flow of your document right you are you are removing you are playing around
with that document flow mostly people what they do is like they deal uh use position for headers
footers and menu sort of fields okay and there are some things right like like fixed and sticky
they use it but if you want to use position people are using relative because if you want to move
like let's say you want you said you told that you want to move it from left or right of that
particular uh existing position then you can use relative you can make that position as
relative and move left and right okay that you can do but like there if you again if you use
absolute somewhere below that things will overlap it's up to you if you are designing how you want
to do it but if you are using margin right margin left that is again a box model which that space
will be consumed okay you have to decide your way of designing like with how you want to pick it up
but if i'm at your place i would go ahead with the position but i want to see your exact use
case like how when you are using it is that answered some bit can i take it as answer
yeah with because that will clutter it right that will clutter it like you have to see uh
like because if you if you don't take care of other elements they can overlap and you
may not be able to see because how this happens it right the fixed and uh the sticky one if you
see absolute one they are removed from their existing position and they come over the layer
on a different layer they come on to the different layer and they behave like these are like html is
of two layered uh pages on a viewport so there's a one page running on the bottom there are some
elements that you defined with position are running on the different layer this happens
this happens because you told that here there is an existing flow but i want to remove from
their existing flow and move it to the different position using top right bottom left so you have
to think uh from the viewer perspective because we are viewing in 2d 2d format now let's say i
open this right i open this itself uh let me say open in live server
uh give me a second i'll show you why you need to think it in uh other elements also
let's say this is a thing available for us
which one i opened sticky one is it
okay let's keep it this way okay now there is something called layers
now if you go and open this okay till the third part and i do something like let's say i
let's say if i bend down and i use scroll a bit of a scroll
if you see that third part right here below i'm not sure if you can see it because it's really
small like you you can use this layers section and you can rotate and you can see that how
it is actually changing let's say even if i remove paint it will be black in color but i can show
like how that are coming over each other so you have to play around with that other elements
also if you're using position okay something but most of the time right
um i mean i use uh like only for headers and footers position but mostly
grids and display flexes flex pause are solving most of the problems right
right yeah z position by z position is uh is z index is different one uh that is for multi-layer
whether you want to show priority order how we want to show it that that i agree upendra
but this generally what happens let's say if i open the other one absolute let's say i open this one
so again
it's just that you can you would be able to see it in your screen i'm not sure if i'll be able
to zoom it this part right let's say i paint this uh i mean
you will be actually able to see how they are actually behaving but guys you can explore this
layers actually how can you use it uh i can show that like how layers you can see in the screen
different screens because generally they whenever you define this property they are coming from the
actual flow uh then out of the flow and they're sticking to that question it is converted into
sticking to that question it is converted into two layers screen and z index will uh
yeah you can explore layers there are too many things to explore we'll explore one by one i've
just shown uh elements and i didn't even talk about computed actually what computed does
i'll talk about this computed in next class like how computed works there are too many things to
explore somebody will explore step by step
huh uh yep and uh any other so ankit was saying sir i'm working on a project of mine using
wordpress wordpress i never used it uh okay but what's your doubt i can take it if you have
anything specific to it
okay yeah anything if you want to add on that
i was just confused for the positioning okay uh okay great great if you are clear that's
that's super great thank you so anything else guys anything else you have i'll push the code
yeah thank you ankit hope you enjoyed it keep attending keep solving assignments guys which
will you know uh actually i wanted to keep one reading session uh earlier i used to take morning
batch so on saturday uh i used to have one document reading session but when we have saturday class
it's night it's 12 o'clock people are in weekend mode uh i'm not sure if i'm even if i open an
article where i can read or something related to front end or back end how many people are going
to be there i mean i had a habit of doing that one uh but anyways i'll i'll try to say uh you know
share uh articles in that whatsapp group where you can go through whatever i'm reading right content
related to web
if anyone is also exploring something they can also drop i can read it can understand
thank you sam
uh one okay um not take it's getting difficult to remember htmlc syntax tags any suggestions
class concept here but takes time uh from what uh i carry four plus uh i remember concepts
i refer to still syntaxes okay never worry that if you are not able to remember syntax
because there are too many things to remember from too many things like uh how many of you
how many will remember like i've told i have only today if we pick up css right i have discussed
for text i've discussed seven to eight properties for display i discussed uh four properties i mean
values for property there are too many things will be coming even if you go for further class
right it will be difficult but what's uh you know uh you need not to mug up anything i would say
that concept keep it clear you should be able to figure out how you can do it even in interviews
right uh i mean uh interviewer should allow like if you remember if you know the basic syntaxes
but there is some syntax that you don't remember you can communicate with him he'll help you out
or you can go and copy uh like check on it you can google it because once one is not supposed
to mug up uh syntaxes basics should be clear concept should be clear you can always refer okay
because a web uh in a way web development is very much huge guys very much huge whatever the
the content that i'm discussing would be overwhelming in itself but i would say that
we are covering uh not completely in depth i'm trying to pick up easy examples such that you
are able to get that concept clear first once the concept is clear then uh then you can go
in depth and experiment with that part okay uh how will be interview task uh upendra mostly
from find and write uh or full stack level those are mainly based on machine coding
uh when it comes to machine coding you are supposed to build html css and javascript
if it is they are talking about vanilla js or else uh they might go to react specific machine
coding i will be sharing those parts like how can you prepare for that how can i help you that
okay we'll see we'll solve some of the machine coding rounds machine coding problems also
okay interesting problems but for that i have to build all the basics for you like
all the html css javascript once i cover basics of these three then you we can will do some
machines coding solve problems in uh using plain vanilla js then we'll learn react then we'll do
some more machine coding related uh problems in react then we'll build some projects also
then we'll go to node js so it's a huge module too many things to cover i'll try my best and
also keep sharing extra things that how you can you keep yourself focused and keep learning
works upendra there will be theoretical rounds too
but something where much will be deciding will be machine coding rounds
thank you
and
so hello guys then uh hope you have a you know take a rest
solve assignments see you on thursday where we'll introduce one of the much interesting topic which
is flexbox which you will be using in day in day out like once you start your journey
if you are writing css uh 70 percent of time you are going to deal with flexbox which i feel it
because that's how my journey has been uh okay so come back uh and try to understand everything
revise this content if you have any doubts bring back me pull pull me in that whatsapp also if you
want to learn anything new tag me there we'll explore things okay so see you on thursday guys
hope you solve assignments and meet you on okay meet you there so hello guys good night take care
stopping screen share
good night
you
You